David Homer Bates Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
David Homer Bates Papers 1837-1926
MSS61627
Bates, David Homer, b. 1843
2 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Telegrapher. Microfilm of correspondence, diary, journal, facsimiles, photographs, newspaper clippings, printed matter, and drafts and annotated proof sheets of Bates’s writings. Includes eleven Abraham Lincoln manuscripts. Forms part of Alfred Whital Stern collection of Lincolniana in the Rare Book and Special Collections Division of the Library.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bates, David Homer, 1843-1926.; Carnegie, Andrew, 1835-1919--Correspondence.; Davis, Jefferson Columbus, 1828-1879--Correspondence.; Eckert, Thomas Thompson, 1825-1910--Correspondence.; Ewell, Richard Stoddert, 1817-1872--Correspondence.; Kemper, James Lawson, 1823-1895--Correspondence.; Kirby-Smith, Edmund, 1824-1893--Correspondence.; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870--Correspondence.; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865. Abraham Lincoln papers. 1861-1865.; Lincoln, Robert Todd, 1843-1926--Correspondence.
Organizations
United States. War Department.
Subjects
Military telegraph.
Places
United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Military intelligence.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Occupations
Telegraphers.
Provenance
The microfilm of the papers of David Homer Bates, telegrapher, consists of reproductions of originals purchased by the Library of Congress in 1962 and held by the Rare Book and Special Collections Division as part of its Alfred Whital Stern Collection of Lincolniana. The microfilm was produced in 1984.
Transfers
The originals are held by the Rare Book and Special Collections Division as part of its Alfred Whital Stern Collection of Lincolniana.
Access and Restrictions
The microfilm copies of the papers of David Homer Bates are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of these papers is available on two reels. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1843, July 3 Born, Steubenville, Ohio
1861 1866 Cipher operator and manager of the War Department's telegraph office
1867 Married Sallie J. Raphael Kenney
1907 Published Lincoln in the Telegraph Office. New York: Century Co.
1926 Published Lincoln Stories Told by Him in the Military Office in the War Department during the Civil War. New York: W. E. Rudge
1926, June l5 Died
Scope and Content Note
The microfilm of the papers of David Homer Bates (1843-1926) spans the years 1837-1926 and consists of reproductions of collected items as well as the personal papers of Bates that comprise part of the Alfred Whital Stern Collection of Lincolniana in the Rare Book and Special Collections Division of the Library. Included are a diary, correspondence, facsimiles, photographs, newspaper clippings, printed matter, and drafts and annotated proof sheets of some of Bates's writings. The papers are organized into the following series: Civil War File, Correspondence, Fascimiles, Miscellany, and Scrapbooks.
Notable among the collected items are eleven Abraham Lincoln manuscripts and single letters of such Civil War commanders as Robert E. Lee, James Lawson Kemper, Edmund Kirby-Smith, Richard Stoddert Ewell, and Jefferson Columbus Davis.
Among the personal papers is a diary and daily journal kept by Bates for the period November 1863 to June 1865, while he served as manager of the War Department telegraph office in Washington, D.C. This volume is of importance as a record of military intelligence activities in the Civil War and is of further interest because of the manner in which the day-to-day narrative reveals the significance of telegraphic communication in the area of military science. Also included in the personal papers are letters of Andrew Carnegie, Thomas Thompson Eckert, and Robert Todd Lincoln. There are also some retained copies of letters written by Bates.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in five series:
Civil War File, 1861-1865
Correspondence, 1864-1926
Facsimiles, 1862-1865
Miscellany, 1837-1926
Scrapbooks, 1907-1908
Container List
Available on microfilm. Shelf no. 18,925
- Civil War File, 1861-1865 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  Notes, letters, and endorsements of Abraham Lincoln, letters of Civil War commanders, diary and daily journal of Bates, and miscellaneous items
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Abraham Lincoln items, including: (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Lincoln, Abraham, to secretary of war, July 25, 1862 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Lincoln, Abraham, to secretary of war, Aug. 7, 1862, with endorsement on letter from Thomas H. Hick to S. Cameron, Nov. 27, 1861 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Lincoln, Abraham, to _______, Aug. 13, 1862 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Lincoln, Abraham, to secretary of war, Aug. 26, 1862 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Lincoln, Abraham, to _______, Oct. 9, 1862, with endorsement on envelope (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Lincoln, Abraham, to secretary of war, Dec. 17, 1862 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Lincoln, Abraham, endorsement on letter from Alex. Williamson to president, Nov. 13, 1863 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Lincoln, Abraham, to _______, Sept. 20, 1864 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Lincoln, Abraham, to secretary of war, Oct. 31, 1864 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Lincoln, Mary Todd, to Mrs. C. Sumwault, Apr. 20, 1864 (original telegram in handwriting of Abraham Lincoln) (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Lincoln, Abraham, Feb. 1865 (signature only) (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Civil War commanders' letters (one each) of Franklin Buchanan, Jefferson C. Davis, Jubal A. Early, Richard S. Ewell, James L. Kemper, E. Kirby-Smith, Robert E. Lee, Gideon J. Pillow, and Richard Taylor (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Diary and daily journal of Bates, 1863-1865 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Reel 1)
- Correspondence, 1864-1926 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  Letters sent and received, mostly the correspondence of Bates with various individuals.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent and thereunder chronologically.
  - Bates, David Homer, 1865-1925, undated (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Carnegie, Andrew, 1868-1910 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Eckert, Thomas T., 1866-1910 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Lincoln, Robert Todd, 1907-1910 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Morse, Samuel Finley Breese, 1864-1906 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - General, 1868-1926 (Box 1, Reel 1)
- Facsimiles, 1862-1865 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  Reproductions of notes, letters, and other items of Abraham Lincoln, Confederate cipher codes, and miscellaneous material.
  - Abraham Lincoln items, including: (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Lincoln, Abraham to Colonel Haupt, Aug. 31, 1862 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Lincoln, Abraham, to Robert A. Maxwell, Sept. 23, 1863 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Lincoln, Abraham, from Robert A. Maxwell, Sept. 23, 1863 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Lincoln, Abraham, to Mary Todd Lincoln, Apr. 27, 1865 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Lincoln, Abraham, to secretary of war, Apr. 3, 1865 (8:00 a.m) (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Lincoln, Abraham, to secretary of war, Apr. 3, 1865 (5:00 p.m.) (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Lincoln, Abraham, autograph estimate of the electoral vote of 1864, with documentation (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Confederate cipher codes (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Reel 1)
- Miscellany, 1837-1926 (Box 2, Reel 1)
  Articles, addresses, books, biographical material, photographs, and miscellaneous items.
  - Articles, addresses, and books (Box 2, Reel 1)
    - Regarding Abraham Lincoln's assassination, Lincoln and the telegraph office, and other Lincoln stories, (3 folders) (Box 2, Reel 1)
    - Regarding Thomas T. Eckert (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - Biographical material on Bates, photographs, fragment related to the presidential campaign of 1844, invitation to the National Inauguration Ball of 1865, and miscellaneous items (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - Contract with the Century Co. for Lincoln in the Telegraph Office and related memoranda, 1906-1920 (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - Envelopes and clippings (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1861-1926 (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - Printed matter (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - School books of John Robert Kenney, 1837, (2 vols.) (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - Tradesmen’s National Bank liquidation papers, 1898-1909 (Box 2, Reel 1)
- Scrapbooks, 1907-1908 (Box 2, Reel 2)
  Two scrapbooks containing magazine and newspaper clippings, letters, and other items related to Lincoln in the Telegraph Office.
  - Magazine and newspaper clippings and letters concerning Lincoln in the Telegraph Office, originals and copies, 1907-1908, (2 vols., partially indexed) (Box 2, Reel 2)